Okay, share this side. Welcome to
concept encoding and today is the last
video of spring boot security. Right. So
we have already covered most of the
frequently asked and used authentication
types and we have also seen one type of
authorization which we used to put at
the security filter layer itself. Okay.
So today we will do the authorization at
the annotation level. We will see that.
So we as I already told you we have
already covered how at security filter
layer we can do the authorization. If
you remember this code you know that
right in the security config class we
used to do like this request matcher
this API should have this role. Okay. So
this is we used to do at a security
filter layer but it has certain
challenges in large scale application
where we used to have hundreds of API.
You might think does any orgs has
hundreds of API? Yes. Right. There are
many orgs which has hundreds of APIs. In
that scenario managing the roles at
security filter might become difficult
and cause a scalable issue. Just
consider that you have all the APIs
listing in your security filter chain
itself and you are providing the roles
here. So what is the better solution?
The better solution is that the place
where we have defined our
endpoint generally at
controller can we at that point itself
we tell what is the
authorization required for it. Okay. So
means at controller layer at controller
layer we can define the
authorization okay and that's where our
annotations comes into the
picture. So here if you see this diagram
once this is I have taken from our
previous authentication. So what I
wanted to show you here is that once a
user is authenticated let's say user one
is getting
authenticated the authentication the
full authentication has all the objects
let's say granted authorities like
whatever the roles we have defined
everything is present inside it right
all the and the same authentication
object reaches till
your controller level. So at controller
level we will use this authentication
object and do the
authorization. So see this in the
annotation based role based
authorization there are two
annotations which are primary used at
the rate pre-authorize and add the rate
post
authorize. Pre-authorize means do the
authorization before execution of the
API logic. Before execution of the API
do the
authorization and post authorize means
does authorization after execution of
the API. So sometime what happen is you
have a business logic. Let's say this is
your endpoint user endpoint. So sometime
is you need to execute the code logic
and whatever the response you are
getting inside that it might have
certain data which we have to use and
based on that we have to do the
authorization logic authorization logic
and then decide do we have to allow the
user to access this API or not. Okay. So
business logic runs first, authorization
happens later in the authorized, post
authorize and in pre-authorize
authorization logic happen first and
then only the API get executed. So first
thing first we will see this annotation
based authorization but first we have to
create a user. So let's create a dynamic
user. I have already shared this uh
username and password creation video
that how you can create a user
dynamically. So here what I am doing is
I am creating one table user login and
in that I have id username
password role and permission. So here
it's like what I'm trying to do is let
let's say user is
shange let me it has a role user it has
a
role
user but I can give I want to give only
permission on let's say order
API read I want to give this and let's
say I want to give
order delete
request or let's say sales post
something you can say that uh sales
create permission and but that's all so
here if if you see I want to do this
authorization like this even though my
role is user inside that also I want to
control yeah even though you are a user
role but only this thing you can do you
can read the orders you You can delete
the order but you can't create it but
yeah you can create
sales. So that way I want to create so
there what I have done is while creating
a user I have a username I have password
role either it could be user it could be
admin and for this role what all the
permission user has. So I have created
is one to many relationship. So I have
created a user permission. It is also
has ID and name. Okay.
So one user can have many permissions
like order read, sales read you can say
that it's like a more granular level we
can give here and here it is little bit
at the top level user and user is what
all granular level permission we can
provide
here. Okay. So these two tables I
created
it and here in the entity service. So
this is our entity service. In the
entity service you already know that we
have to implement the user detail
service. We have to override this load
by username and this is to save. This is
repository and this is the controller
through which I have to create a user.
So this is already we have seen like uh
here in this video. Okay. So one thing I
will come to this point later but one
thing you notice this part we have also
seen that in the previous video but here
if you see in the get
authorities okay when you are
implementing the user details right we
have to override this method get
authorities okay so this is the same
thing here if you see in the
authentication object there is something
called granted authorities this got
filled up from this
itself. Okay, this got filled from this
itself granted
authorities. So here if you see I am
putting my role and also I am putting
all my permission. So this
list whatever this authentication will
go here right ultimately in the
authentication object this list will
have everything let's say role
user
comma
order
reada sales create so everything will
comes inside this granted authorities of
authentication object okay so that's why
in the same granted get authorities in
the same list I am putting my roles and
I am putting all my permissions also
okay so that's what I'm
doing so now let's
see now we should be able to create
user okay so here I am hitting this
endpoint user
login and my username let's say SJ
password is let's say 1 2 3 role I am
giving ro user
Okay. And permission I am giving only
one permission that is order read. Okay.
And user is
created. Now the user creation part is
done. We can update our security config
file
also. So in the security config file we
have to enable this annotation. Enable
method security preost enable equals to
true. Okay. Without enabling this the
pre authorized and post authorized
annotation would be
ignored. Okay. So in the security config
we have to tell that pre-post enabled
equals to true. Then only this
annotation would get
intercepted.
Okay. So currently I am doing basic
authentic authentication just for
testing. You can do with anything this
annotation testing with JWT oath or this
thing. But currently I'm testing for the
simplicity basic authentication. Okay,
because our purpose is to do
authorization not
authentication. So yeah this is the
changes we have to do in security
config. We have to enable the pre-post
enabled to
true. And for testing purpose I have
created two controller one order and one
for sales. So here if you see this is my
one
endpoint slash orders. Okay. A / API/
orders and this is just I have let's say
that all orders have been fetched
successfully. Okay. We can make it
dynamic. We will hit DB f the data but
for now for simplicity because this is
not our main purpose. Our main purpose
is
this. Okay. So I have used the
annotation on top of
this method in the controller class at
the rate pre-authorize.
Now here if you see I have used like has
ro user I haven't put rod because inside
the has ro has ro this is by default get
added okay so you have to just put has
ro user what is the role we want to give
user and authority I want to give order
read okay and similarly for the
sales/ ai/ sales I have used at the rate
pre-authorized annotation and I put that
no matter whatever the role you have
this has authority you should have this
authority
sales_read
okay
and we have already created a user which
has both ro user and order read
permission. So this is the place where
we have created a user right this user
is created what is the role rod user and
what is the permission it has order
read okay so this is totally qualified
for this one order controller because it
has the user role and it has order read
also for sales it required sales read
permission which doesn't have Okay. So
now let's say that I am trying to access
an API slash order/ API/ orderer API.
Since it's a basic authentication, I am
providing the username password SJ123.
This is what I have created a user as
username
password. Okay. And when I hit it, all
orders have been fed
successfully. But when I try to access
the sales API/ API/ sales if you see the
same username password I got forbidden.
Why? Because this
required permission sales read which
this user doesn't have. This user has
only order read and user
permission. Okay.
Now at one at this point of time before
proceeding
further you might get one question what
is the difference between has role and
has authority. If you remember I have
already explained that in the part where
we have done the authority at the
authorization at the security filter
layer but again I will tell at code
level it has no
difference okay only difference is that
when you use has role it will append
roders that's all for authority it do
not append anything whatever you give it
will be used like
that okay no difference and everything
whatever the role whatever the authority
you have defined everything will get
appended into a single list
only okay I will show you the code also
inside has role also uses the same code
authority you calls the same code itself
okay so it just like for us very high
level you can use role for high level
distinction and authority has authority
for the gr granular level distinction.
Okay. But at the code level, if you go
one step down, you will see no
difference. Everything would be inside a
list only. Ro, rod user and whatever the
authority you will define. Let's say
order, create, sales, read, everything
would be like for this user. These are
the all the permissions. Same thing I
have mentioned here. Spring Boot treats
both has role and has authority in a
similar way. Only difference is that for
has role rod is appended. So see this
code if you open this security
expression root on java it has has
authority has authority calls has any
authority it calls this and has any
authority called has any authority name
it ultimately calls this
method and when you use has role
internally it called has any role this
and has any role calls the same
ultimately no matter what you used has
authority or has role both involves the
same code. Only difference is that when
you use has role right it put a default
role prefix which is nothing but a role
underscore but ultimately it would have
is that a list of get authority
set right it will get a list of get
authority set. So what would happen
is so here if you go while user
creation we have given the right get
authorities so here I am returning the
authorities this authorities will have a
role plus this permissions so internally
what it does here
is it will get in in this list it will
have everything role plus authorities
generally both are same so but it has
the complete list role admin comma all
this thing. Now it just check it will
iterate that hey does user has this role
which is contained in the list or not.
So now here in this case what generally
happened is you put has role user. So
internally it automatically appended
this default prefix. So it has put rod
user. Now it will check does this
present inside this list? Yes. Then it
goes to the next one authority order
read for order read has authority
doesn't append anything. So it will
directly check the same list what the
same list has this order read also if
yes then ultimately return true. So you
understand that has role has authority
has no difference only thing is the
prefix get appended into the has role.
So you we don't need to add ro
underscore it will get automatically
added
but we generally use has role for high
level distinction and has authority for
more granular level distinction.
Okay. Now one questions comes to our
mind is how this authorization method
invokes before invocation of a
controller method. So this is is
returning true and false right in the
security expression root. So has role
method get get invoked because in the
pre-authorized annotation I have put has
role has authority. So these methods are
getting invoked. So how this get
invoked? Who is taking care of it? So
remember this diagram. So that's where I
have also explained in previous videos
of this spring boot
interceptors right I have explained
about the interceptor. So pre-authorized
annotation is intercepted by this class
authorization manager before method
interceptor. Okay. So this intercept
this
annotation and how the interception
works. How we can create write our own
interceptors. What is the difference
between filters and interceptors? I we
have already covered this in depth one
interceptor video and the filter versus
interceptor. You will see how exactly
the interceptor works. How we can create
our own interceptors. We have already
seen that. Okay. So this is one of the
interceptors which tracks this
annotation. So if you remember we have
also created one interceptor we which
tracks different annotation. So
similarly this annotation is already
there in the spring security framework
which track this annotation
authorization manager before method
interceptor. Okay. So we know that okay
this is the this annotation got
intercepted by
authorization manager before method
interceptor. Now what it will do? Now
what it will do is this whatever the
string you provide inside
this this is generally known as a spring
expression language
spel a spring expression language okay
so generally what happened is when this
interceptor got invoked because of this
pre authorized
annotation it first read the string from
this annotation so it read this string
Okay. So currently it's in a string
format. Now what it will do is it will
pass it to the spell expression
parser. So there is a parser provided by
the spring security framework which is
spell parser. A spell expression parser.
So what it do is it will convert this
string to a abstract syntax tree. So now
you will see the tree like this. What is
the operation? End. This is the
operation end. So it's left left operand
right operand. Okay. So it's at a
children. This is children zero. This is
children one. So left operand right
operent. Okay. So here it has end which
is operation end. So it has this invoke
this class which internally does this
left operand right operent part the same
thing. So what I'm trying to say that we
don't have to write any of this thing it
recursively resolve this
expression. Okay so right it's a
operation end. So it invokes this method
then it's resolved its left operand.
Left operent is your this zero
part and again if you see this if you go
inside this left operent again it's a
recursive call. If there is any other
operand let's say or so it will goes to
that class that will have left right
likewise and once that is resolved then
it will automatically resolve the right
oper and the same recursive operations
happen and ultimately what it does is
once it invokes all the method all the
variables references right ultimately
what it will do is this interceptor
validate the result and decide whether
to invoke the method or not. So these
are the steps involved once the
interceptor is invoked. So we can use
more logical operation like currently we
have used end right like has role and we
have put and has authority. Similarly we
can use or we can use not and similarly
we have relational operator we can use
like this value. So generally in the API
slash user slash you might have some
let's say ID. So we can also read we can
put
authorization logic on this value also.
Okay. So value is 15 value not equals to
15. I'll tell you when this comes into
the picture like when it would be
helpful for us. Just for example let's
say I have created this
endpoint fetch user details. What is
this path variable? Path variable is ID.
So the same ID I used here. ID should be
this. Okay. Is this
pre-authorize post authorize has access
to your authentication object. Okay. We
can see that. So if you open the code
you can open that uh what was that
authorization manager before method
interceptor right so this is the attempt
authorization will ultimately get
invoked and attempt authorization if you
see that it has like get
authentication right so in the get au
authentication security context holder
strategy which we have put into the
filter part okay from there it has the
complete authentication
object. Now based on that uh so it has
access to the authentication object. So
based on
that if you want to put any logic we can
put like this. So here if you remember
that let's say I have created one user
let's say RJ password is 1 2 3 and in
DB and in DB it would be like
ID1 RJ username password is 1 2 3. So
this ID also comes this this is uni
unique user ID. So this ultimately
generally called as principal ID. Okay.
So let's say that I want to make sure
that whatever the user it is trying to
fetch an ID. This should be the same
user who is
authenticated. Okay. So in basic
authentication you are putting RJ and
the password 1 2 3 right username
password for the basic authentication
when hitting any API. So first it goes
to the filter f the authentication
object and that authentication object
get principle authentication it has this
let's say ID this is the second user
username is this password is
this now I want to make sure that this
API which is getting it is trying to hit
let's say this user is calling an
endpoint/
user/3 but this user is unique user ID
is two so I should not allow this user
to hit the endpoint to fetch the details
of some other user. So that's why I put
this like okay check
this whatever the ID user is trying to
fetch in this endpoint is the same as
what the principal ID what is this user
who is actually authenticated. So that
way you can also use so post authorize
is very very similar. So only thing is
it does the authorization after
execution of the API but before sending
the response back to the
user and what is the interceptor
authorization manager after method
interceptor comes into the picture
after. So we can see this like I have
created two users just for testing
purpose. So I have created A user role
uh password 1 2 3 and it has role user
and order
read with the same role and permission I
have created B user. So in DB it has uh
A user has unique ID 1 and B user has
unique ID 2. Okay.
Now I am creating one
controller let's say read order endpoint
/ API/
orderer. So in the pre-authorize I have
put that user should has role user. So
here if you see both has role user. This
is also role user. This is also role
user and should have authority order
read. Okay. So this is a read API. Get
read API. get call orders. So they
should have order read permission. Both
have order
read.
Okay. Now let's come to post authorized
later. Now what would happen when you
hit this
endpoint / API/order who is trying to
access B user 1 2 3 it is trying to hit.
What would happen? The first
pre-authorized will interceptor will get
invoked. It will check does B user has
the role user? Yes. Does B user has
order read permission? Yes. Then it will
go and execute this. So now in this one
for hard-coded purpose I have created
the order DTO and put a user ID
one. Okay. and order id this that this
order belongs to user id one and
returning the
dto. Now here I have used post authorize
annotation. So what happen is in this
post authorize there is something called
return object. Return object it could be
if you're using a string if you're using
any
object it internally type casted for us.
We don't have to do that. we only have
to use return
object. So now I am checking
that whatever the user who is
authenticated and calling the endpoint.
So here in this B
user this B B user this unique ID is
two. So this user should only get its
its own order not somebody else order
and this order contains for hardcoded
purpose I have put that this order
belongs to user ID 1. So now what I'm in
the post authorize I'm checking the
return object. So this order DTO
internally type cast for us order
DTO dot user id dot user id equals to
equals to authentication.principle
principal do id. So authentication
dotprinciple do id for this b
user the id would be this two. So this 1
equals to equals to two. No. So means
this user is trying to access the data
of some other user. So it return
forbid. But if I use the a
user it return me the data. Why? because
uh a user principal id is
one and here in the hard-coded way I
have put user id one only. So they got
matched. So here if you see that in the
post authorize what I just wanted to
tell it access the code and before
returning to the end user it has
intercepted our return
object from there whatever the field we
want to check with the
data. Okay we can do that logic and then
only it will provide the response to the
user.
Okay. Okay guys, if you have any doubt,
let me know. We can discuss further more
in the comment section. Thank you. Bye.